Finding Aid for Sarah Goodard Power Papers 1953-1987
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
Sarah Goddard Power Papers
1953-1987
Power, Sarah Goddard, 1935-1987.
Regent of the University of Michigan; public figure concerned with national and international women's rights issues. Files relating to her public life, especially her interest in the University of Michigan, notably during the presidency of Harold T. Shapiro, the work of the United Nations Educational, Scientific, and Cultural Organization, and state and local Democratic Party matters.
8852 Aa 2
10 linear feet
Bentley Historical Library University of Michigan
Portions of the collection were donated by Sarah Goddard Power (donor no. 6280 ) in February 1987; additional materials came from Philip Power in July 1987.
The collection is open for research.
Sarah Goddard Power was born June 19, 1935. She graduated from Vassar College in 1957 with a bachelors in history and from New York University in 1965 with a masters in Politics and International Relations. From 1966 to 1969 Power was executive director of the New York City Commission for the United Nations.
In 1974, Power was elected regent of the University of Michigan, a post she held for thirteen years. Previous to her election as regent, Power was assistant chairwoman of the University of Michigan's Commission for Women. As a regent Power supported liberal causes, such as affirmative action, women's issues, and the increased enrollment of Blacks.
A long-time advocate of the work of the United Nations, Power was especially supportive of the United Nations Educational, Scientific, and Cultural Organization (UNESCO). This agency, she believed, was the most effective in working to establish world peace. In 1976 and 1978 Power represented the United States at the 19th and 20th general UNESCO conferences. She served as vice-chairman of the U.S. National Commission for UNESCO from 1975 to 1976 and as chairman from 1976 to 1979. In addition, she was delegate to two UN Conferences for the Decade for Women (1975 and 1980).
Power was also actively involved with the Democratic Party at the local and state and national levels. She further served her nation as deputy assistant secretary of state for human rights and social affairs from 1980 to 1981.
In 1971 she married Philip H. Power. They had one son, Nathan. Sarah Goddard Power died March 24, 1987.
The papers of Sarah Goddard Power are arranged into twelve series: Personal/Biographical, Writings, Speeches, Contributions, Trips, Political Activities, Conferences, Philip H. Power, Board of Regents, Photographs, Engagements, and U.S. National Commission for UNESCO. These series cover the period 1953-1987.
Subjects:
Civic leaders--Michigan.; Democratic Party (Mich.); Power, Sarah Goddard, 1935-1987.; Shapiro, Harold T., 1935-; UNESCO.; University of Michigan--Administration.Administration.; University of Michigan. Board of Regents.; Women civic leaders--Michigan.; Women in politics--Michigan.; Women's rights.
Subjects - Visual Material:
African Americans.; Ford, Betty, 1918-2011.; Ford, Gerald R., 1913-2006.; Friedan, Betty.; Griffiths, Martha W. (Martha Wright), 1912-2003.; Iacocca, Lee A.; Mondale, Joan Adams, 1930-; Mondale, Walter F., 1928-; Muskie, Edmund S., 1914-1996; Power, Philip H.; Power, Sarah Goddard, 1935-1987.; Shapiro, Harold T., 1935-; UNESCO.; University of Michigan. Board of Regents.; University of Michigan--Commencements.Commencements.; University of Michigan--Students.Students.; Women--Political life.; Women's rights.
Subjects--Sound Recordings
Power, Sarah Goddard, 1935-1987.; University of Michigan. Board of Regents.; University of Michigan--Commencements--1976.1976.Commencements; University of Michigan--Commencements--1979.Commencements1979.
Genre/Form:
Photographs.; Sound recordings.
- Personal/Biographical, 1953-1987
  Personal/Biographical consists of two-thirds of a linear foot of materials, primarily consisting of manuscripts and clippings arranged in chronological order. The clippings are of most interest to researchers as they contain the longest and most encompassing documentation of Power's life.
  - Academic Women's Caucus: Sarah Power Award, 1988 (Box 1)
  - Awards and Membership (Box 1)
  - Biographical, General (Box 1)
  - Detroit University School Yearbook, 1953 (Box 1)
  - Diary of Trip to Europe, 1958-1959 (Box 1)
  - Master's Thesis, New York University, October 1965; 1 folders; 3 volumes (Box 1)
  - Clippings
    - 1968-1979 (Box 1)
    - 1980-1982 (Box 1)
    - 1983-1986 (Box 1)
    - And Eulogy, 1987 (Box 1)
  - Correspondence, 1959-1967 (Box 1)
  - Resumes and Related Materials (Box 1)
- Writings
  - Articles by Sarah G. Power, 1981-1987 (Box 1)
  - Testimonies for UNESCO, 1977-1981 (Box 1)
- Speeches
  - 1968-1975 (Box 1)
  - 1976-1977
    - Manuscripts of Speeches (Box 1)
    - Tape of Winter Commencement Speech, University of (Box 1)
    - Michigan with Mrs. Ford's Remark, May 1976 (Box 1)
  - 1978-1979
    - Manuscripts of Speeches (Box 2)
    - Tape of Winter Commencement Speech, University of Michigan, May 1979 (Box 2)
  - 1980
    - Manuscripts of Speeches (Box 2)
    - Tape of Focus radio interview, September 19, 1980 (Box 2)
  - 1981-1982 (Box 2)
  - 1983 (Box 2)
  - 1984 (Box 2)
  - 1985-1987 (Box 2)
    (includes remarks at Academic Women's Caucus, 1987)
- Contributions
  - Charitable Education and International Groups (Box 2)
  - Miscellaneous (Box 2)
  - Political Individual Candidates, A-Z (Box 2)
  - Political Organizations (Box 2)
  - University of Michigan (Box 2)
  - Women's Organizations (Box 2)
- Trips
  - Family Safari in Africa, 1972 (Box 2)
  - NATO Trip, October 12-25, 1975 (Box 2)
  - Chinese Trip, February 10-27, 1976 (Box 2)
- Political Activities, 1974-1986
  Political Activities consists of nearly one linear foot of manuscripts and notes. The series is divided into several subseries: Regent Campaign 1974, Regent Campaign 1982, Campaign for Congress in the Second Congressional District (exploring possibility of running for Congress), consideration as U.S. Delegate to the Economic and Social Council of the UCOSOC), Deputy Assistant Secretary of State for Human Rights and Social Affairs, and State and Local Politics. Of most interest here to researchers are the Regent Campaigns of 1974 and 1982 files which document some of her regental activities.
  - Regent Campaign, 1974
    - Appearances and Remarks (Box 2)
    - Democratic State Convention (Box 2)
    - Election, Certificate of (Box 2)
    - Election Results (Box 2)
    - Endorsements (Box 2)
    - Financial Disclosure (Box 2)
      (see also Box 1 Clippings)
    - Financial Expenses (Box 2)
    - Fundraiser; The Tree House Party, July 1974 (Box 2)
    - Literature and Mailing (Box 2)
    - Memorabilia (Box 2)
    - Staff Meeting Minutes (Box 2)
    - Support Committee (Box 2)
  - Regent Campaign, 1982
    - Announcement (Box 2)
    - Appearances and Remarks (Box 2)
    - Campaign Chronology (Box 2)
    - Campaign Issues (Box 2)
    - Democratic State Convention (Box 2)
    - Election, Certificate of (Box 3)
    - Election Results (Box 3)
    - Endorsements (Box 3)
      see also Box 1 Clippings
    - Financial Expenses (Box 3)
    - Fundraisers
      - Summary of and Thurber's, June 1982 (Box 3)
      - Martha Griffiths, October 1982 (Box 3)
    - Literature and Mailing (Box 3)
    - Memorabilia (Box 3)
    - Organization, Statement of (Box 3)
    - Pre-Candidacy (Box 3)
    - Questions (Box 3)
    - Staff Meeting Minutes (Box 3)
    - Staff Strategy and Miscellaneous (Box 3)
    - Support Committee (Box 3)
    - Volunteers (Box 3)
  - Campaign for Congress in the Second Congressional District, 1983-1984 (Box 3)
    exploring possibility of running for Congress
  - Consideration as U.S. Delegate to the Economic and Social Council of the UN (ECOSOC), July 1979-March 1980 (Box 3)
  - Deputy Assistant Secretary of State for Human Rights and Social Affairs, 1980-1981
    - Announcements, May-June 1980 (Box 3)
    - Conflict of Interest as Regent of the University of Michigan, March-July, 1980 (Box 3)
    - Efficiency Reports, August 1980-September 1981 (Box 3)
    - Memorabilia, 1981 (Box 3)
    - Resignation Announcement, February-March, 1981 (Box 3)
    - Transition to Reagan Administration, August 1980-January 1981 (Box 3)
    - Watergate Bash Party, April 1981 (Box 3)
  - State and Local Politics
    - Fundraiser for Marge Lansing, regent of the University of Michigan, September-October, 1984 (Box 3)
    - Homecoming for Governor Jim Blanchard, 1986, September 1986 (Box 3)
- Conferences
  - UNESCO Mass Media Conference, New York City, September 10, 1976; October 8, 1976 (Box 3)
  - World Conference of the U.N. Decade for Women, Copenhagen, 1970 (Box 3)
  - Women's Leadership Conference on National Security, June 1982 (Box 3)
  - UNESCO 21st General Conference, September-October, 1982 (Box 3)
  - Women's Presidential Project, 1983-1984 (Box 3)
  - Women's Assembly III: Platform Issues, June 1984 (Box 3)
  - Forward Looking Strategies Meeting, November 20, 1985 (Box 3)
- Philip H. Power
  - Campaign for U.S. Senate, 1977 (Box 3)
  - General (Box 3)
- Board of Regents
  The Board of Regents series, which consists of about four linear feet of informational materials, memoranda, notes, and clippings, which are subdivided into topical subseries and then arranged alphabetically by topical names. Of special interest here is the documentation on issues of concern to Power and/or University of Michigan students, faculty, and staff during her career, including: Affirmative Action, South Africa, the Student Code of Nonacademic Conduct, and Classified Research. Power also collected clippings and memoranda on and speeches by University of Michigan Presidents Robben W. Fleming and Harold T. Shapiro. These materials should be used by researchers to supplement the records of the president's office at the Michigan Historical Collections.
  - Admissions, General, 1984-1985 (Box 4)
  - Affirmative Action, 1975-1987
    - Compliance with Government Regulations, 1980 (Box 4)
    - Correspondence, 1975-1985 (Box 4)
    - Current Issues, 1982-1987 (Box 4)
    - Gay Rights, 1982-1984 (Box 4)
    - Hospital, University of Michigan, 1976 (Box 4)
    - Minority Affairs, 1979-1987 (Box 4)
    - Office, History of, 1977 (Box 4)
    - Pay Equity, 1985 (Box 4)
    - Personal Notes, 1975-1983 (Box 4)
    - Promotions, 1982-1983 (Box 4)
    - Sexual Assault and Campus Safety, 1985 (Box 4)
    - Sexual Harassment, 1983-1984 (Box 4)
  - Ann Arbor, City of, Relationships with University of Michigan, 1975-1986 (Box 4)
  - Art School, Review of, 1982-1983 (Box 4)
  - Athletics, 1979-1986
    - Future of, 1986 (Box 4)
    - Title IX, 1981-1982 (Box 4)
    - Women's Programs, 1979-1985 (Box 4)
  - Audits, 1978-1986 (Box 4)
  - Business Administration School, 1977-1984
    - Goals of, 1978-1982 (Box 4)
    - Kalmbach Center, 1977-1984 (Box 4)
  - Business, Economics, Finances, 1980-1985
    - Brazer Project, 1980-1981 (Box 4)
    - Budgets, 1982-1985 (Box 4)
    - Computer Fees, 1985 (Box 4)
    - Economic Challenge and the State of Michigan, 1980 (Box 4)
  - Ceremonial: Remarks, spoofs, etc. upon retirement of University officials, 3 folders (Box 4)
  - Child Care, 1975-1982 (Box 4)
  - Commencement, 1976-1986
    - Correspondence, 1984-1986 (Box 4)
    - Francoise Giroud, speaker, Spring 1976 (Box 4)
  - Communications, Department of, 1981-1987
    - Fellowship Program, 1982-1986 (Box 4)
    - General, 1981-1987 (Box 4)
  - Dearborn Campus: Evaluation of Chancellor William Jenkins, 1985 (Box 4)
  - Development Campaign, 1980-1986
    - Communications, Department of, 1985 (Box 4)
    - General, 1983-1984 (Box 4)
    - Hospital, University of Michigan, 1983 (Box 4)
    - Leadership, 1983-1986 (Box 4)
    - Personal Involvement, 1984-1986
      - General, 1984-1986 (Box 4)
      - Chicago, June 6, 1984 (Box 4)
      - Grosse Pointe Dinner, July 10, 1984 (Box 4)
      - University Seminar, February 22, 1985 (Box 4)
      - National Leadership Meeting, October 29, 1985 (Box 4)
      - Williams, G. Mennen, Dinner, June 17, 1986 (Box 4)
    - Vice-President of, 1981-1982 (Box 4)
    - Women, 1980-1983 (Box 4)
  - East Asian Student, Center for, Campaign spans, 1977-1982 (Box 4)
  - Education, School of, 1983 (Box 4)
  - Enrollment, 1985 (Box 4)
  - Executive Officers, 1977-1984
    - Evaluation of, 1983 (Box 4)
    - Salaries of, 1977-1984 (Box 4)
  - Financial Aid, 1974-1986
    - Draft, 1983 (Box 4)
    - General, 1974-1982 (Box 4)
    - Personal Involvement, 1979-1986 (Box 4)
  - Fleming, R.W., 1978-1981
    - General, 1978-1981 (Box 4)
    - Retirement Dinner: Philip and Sarah Power Sketch, undated (Box 4)
  - Flint Campus, 1981-1983
    - General Motors Institute, 1981 (Box 4)
    - Parking Issue, 1983 (Box 4)
    - Physical Therapy Program, 1982-1983 (Box 4)
  - Ford, Gerald R., Library, 1981-1983 (Box 5)
  - Honorary Degrees, 1976-1986 (Box 5)
  - Labor, 1974-1983
    - Collective Bargaining (AFSCME), 1976-1983 (Box 5)
    - Collective Bargaining, GEO, 1974-1977 (Box 5)
    - Collective Bargaining, GEO, 1978-1983 (Box 5)
  - Law School
    - Current State, 1986 (Box 5)
    - Personal Involvement with Ad-missions to, 1983-1984 (Box 5)
  - L.S. and A., 1974-1983
    - Commission on Graduation Requirements, 1974-1975 (Box 5)
    - Pilot Program, 1979-1983 (Box 5)
    - Jewell Cobb Deanship, 1974-1975 (Box 5)
  - Medical Center, Sarah G. Power's Notes, 1975-1987 (Box 5)
  - Natural Resources, School of; Review of, 1983 (Box 5)
  - Power Center for the Performing Arts, 1979-1981 (Box 5)
  - Power Scholarship, 1976-1986 (Box 5)
  - Presidential Search Committee, 1978-1985 (Box 5)
  - Provost and Vice-President for Academic Affairs, Search for, 1985-1986 (Box 5)
  - Public Interest Research Group In Michigan (PIRGIM),Funding of, 1980-1985 (Box 5)
  - Press Freedom Issue: University's Remarks On, 1983 (Box 5)
  - Regents, 1967-1987
    - Community Leader Dinner, 1981 (Box 5)
    - Interviews, 1982-1987 (Box 5)
    - Meetings, 1971-1986
      - Executive Committee, 5 pm., and Deans, 1983-1985 (Box 5)
      - Governor Milliken, July 5, 1979 (Box 5)
      - General, 1981-1983 (Box 5)
      - Informal, 1972-1985 (Box 5)
      - Special, 1986 (Box 5)
    - Personal, 1977-1985
      - Financial Disclosure, 1977 (Box 5)
      - Miscellaneous, 1980-1985 (Box 5)
    - Procedures and Governance, 1967-1973 (Box 5)
    - Retreats, 1975-1982
      - June 8-10, 1975 (Box 5)
      - June 13, 1976 (Box 5)
      - June 5-7, 1977 (Box 5)
      - June 10, 1982 (Box 5)
    - Shapiro, President Harold T., Interim Reports of, 1984-1986 (Box 5)
  - Research, 1971-1987
    - Classified, 1984-1987 (Box 5)
    - Defense, 1982-1983 (Box 5)
    - Environmental Research Institute of Michigan (ERIM), 1972-1977 (Box 6)
    - General, 1974-1987
      - March 1974-June 1983 (Box 6)
      - June 1983-August 1984 (Box 6)
      - November 1984-March 1987 (Box 6)
    - Genetic, 1975-1983
      - December 1975-April 1976 (Box 6)
      - May 1976-December 1983 (Box 6)
    - Intellectual Property, 1985 (Box 6)
    - Michigan Research Corporation, 1983 (Box 6)
    - Nuclear Free Zone, 1984 (Box 6)
    - Peace Studies, Tanter Proposal, 1985 (Box 6)
      see also Speeches for 1985 in Box 1
    - Research Excellence Fund, 1985 (Box 6)
    - Strategic Defense Initiative, General, 1982-1985 (Box 6)
    - Vice-President for, and Consolidation with Rackham, 1971-1984 (Box 6)
  - Shapiro, President Harold T., 1979-1986
    - Clippings on, 1979-1984 (Box 6)
    - Inauguration of, Announcements of, 1979 (Box 6)
    - Inauguration of, Guest List, 1979 (Box 6)
    - Interim Reports of, 1984-1986 (Box 6)
    - Review of Office, 1984-1986 (Box 6)
    - Salary of, 1983-1984 (Box 6)
    - Speeches of, 1981-1984 (Box 6)
  - South Africa
    - Autonomy of the University from, 1978-1986 (Box 6)
    - Committees on University of Michigan, 1978-1983 (Box 6)
    - Correspondence, 1984-1985 (Box 6)
    - Dun and Bradstreet Correspondence, 1982-1983 (Box 6)
    - Fleming, President R.W., Input on, 1978 (Box 6)
    - Free Equity Fund for College, 1985 (Box 7)
    - Meetings to Divest Funds, 1983 (Box 7)
    - Regental Actions Chronology, 1985 (Box 7)
  - State of the University Address, 1969-1985 (Box 7)
  - Students, 1973-1986
    - General, 1984 (Box 7)
    - Bursley Incident, 1981-1982 (Box 7)
    - Code of Nonacademic Conduct, 1973-1985 (Box 7)
    - Publications, 1985-1986 (Box 7)
    - Statistics, 1982 (Box 7)
  - Technology, 1981-1985
    - Industrial Technology Institute (ITI), 1981-1985 (Box 7)
    - Research Parks, General, 1982-1983 (Box 7)
    - Robotics and Integrated Manufacturing, Center for, (CRIM), 1981-1982 (Box 7)
  - Tower Society, ADARA (Box 7)
  - Women's Studies, 1977-1986
    - Black History Project, 1984 (Box 7)
    - General, 1977-1986 (Box 7)
- Photographs
  The photographs series includes formal and informal portraits; photos of Power attending UNESCO and University of Michigan functions; and photos of Power with other public figures, notably Martha Griffiths, Philip H. Power, Edmund Muskie, Walter and Joan Mondale, William Milliken, Gerald and Betty Ford, and Harold Shapiro.
  - Individual, undated (Box 7)
  - Assorted, undated (Box 7)
  - Speeches (Box 7)
  - Trips (Box 7)
  - Regent Campaign, 1982 (Box 7)
  - Deputy Assistant Secretary of State (Box 7)
  - State and Local Politics (Box 7)
  - Conferences (Box 7)
- Engagements
  - 1975-1982 (Box 7)
  - 1983-1987 (Box 8)
- United States National Commission For UNESCO
  The series U.S. National Commission for UNESCO documents Sarah Goddard Power's great interest in, and commitment to, the cause of world press freedom. Included are extensive subject files, correspondence, memoranda, revolutions, and other background materials. Some of the files detail her participation at various U.N. conferences on the subject of the free flow of information among all nations of the world.
  - Files relating to world press freedom, free flow of press information, and other media issues (Box 9)
  - Files relating to world press freedom, free flow of press information, and other media issues (Box 10)
    (continued)